Marco Tempest: What I'd like to show you today
ما أود عرضه عليكم اليوم
is something in the way of an experiment.
هو نوع من تجربة
Today's its debut.
تعرض اليوم لأول مرة
It's a demonstration of augmented reality.
و هي شرح ل "الحقيقة المدمجة".
And the visuals you're about to see are not prerecorded.
و التشكيلات التي ستشاهدونها ليست مسجلة مسبقا
They are live
إنما تعرض عليكم مباشرة
and reacting to me in real time.
و تتفاعل معي بالوقت الحقيقي
I like to think of it as a kind of technological magic.
اعتبرها نوع من التقنية السحرية
So fingers crossed.
لذا تمنوا لي الحظ .
And keep your eyes on the big screen.
و إبقوا أعينكم على الشاشة الكبيرة
Augmented reality
الحقيقة المدمجة :
is the melding of the real world
هي مزج العالم الحقيقي
with computer-generated imagery.
مع صور مكونه من الكومبيوتر.
It seems the perfect medium
يبدو انها الوسط المثالي
to investigate magic
للبحث عن السحر
and ask, why, in a technological age,
و للسؤال، لماذا، في عصر التقنية،
we continue to have
يبقى لدينا
this magical sense of wonder.
هذا الأحساس السحري بالدهشة
Magic is deception,
السحر هو خداع
but it is a deception we enjoy.
لكنه خداع مسلِ
To enjoy being deceived,
كي تستمتع بالأنخداع
an audience must first
يجب على الحضور ،في باديء الأمر،
suspend its disbelief.
ان يقطع الشك .
It was the poet Samuel Taylor Coleridge
كان الشاعر سامويل تايلر كولردج
who first suggested this receptive state of mind.
هو اول من اقترح هذه الحالة الذهنية المتقبلة
Samuel Taylor Coleridge: I try to convey a semblance of truth in my writing
حين قال: أحاول ان انقل ما يشبه الحقيقة في كتاباتي
to produce for these shadows of the imagination
كي أحقق ل ظلال المخيلة
a willing suspension of disbelief
إيقافاً إرادياً للشك
that, for a moment,
هذا ، لبرهة من الزمن،
constitutes poetic faith.
يؤلف الإيمان الشعري.
MT: This faith in the fictional is essential
ماركو: هذا الإيمان بالخيال هو جوهري
for any kind of theatrical experience.
لأي نوع من التجارب المسرحية.
Without it,
و بدونه ،
a script is just words.
يكون النص مجرد كلمات.
Augmented reality
الحقيقة المدمجة
is just the latest technology.
هي مجرد تقنية حديثة.
And sleight of hand
و خفة اليد
is just an artful demonstration
هي مجرد إظهار متقن
of dexterity.
للبراعة.
We are all very good at suspending our disbelief.
كلنا جيدون بتعطيل شكوكنا
We do it every day,
نقوم بذلك كل يوم،
while reading novels,
أثناء قراءة القصص،
watching television
مشاهدة التلفاز،
or going to the movies.
أو الذهاب للسينما.
We willingly enter fictional worlds
ندخل بإرادتنا لعوالم خيالية
where we cheer our heroes
حيث نهتف لإبطالنا
and cry for friends we never had.
و نبكِ لأصدقاء لم نحظَ بهم قط.
Without this ability
بدون هذه القابلية
there is no magic.
لن يكون هنالك سحر.
It was Jean Robert-Houdin,
كان جان روبرت هودين،
France's greatest illusionist,
ساحر فرنسا الأعظم،
who first recognized the role of the magician
هو أول من ميّز دور الساحر
as a storyteller.
ك راوِ قصص.
He said something that I've posted on the wall of my studio.
قال شيئاً قمت بوضعه على جدار الأستوديو الخاص بي
Jean Robert-Houdin: A conjurer is not a juggler.
هودين: الساحر ليس بهلوانياً.
He is an actor playing the part of a magician.
انما هو ممثل يلعب دور الساحر.
MT: Which means magic is theater
ماركو:مما يعني ان السحر هو مسرح
and every trick
و كل خدعة
is a story.
هي قصة.
The tricks of magic
و الخدع السحرية
follow the archetypes of narrative fiction.
تتبع النموذج الأصلي للسرد الأدبي.
There are tales of creation and loss,
ف هناك حكايات الخلق و الخسارة،
death and resurrection,
الموت و الإنبعاث،
and obstacles that must be overcome.
و عراقيل يجب تذليلها.
Now many of them are intensely dramatic.
و الكثير منها دراماتيكية بشدة
Magicians play with fire and steel,
يلعب السحرة بالحديد و النار،
defy the fury of the buzzsaw,
متحدين ضراوة المنشار
dare to catch a bullet
لهم الجرأة لمسك رصاصة
or attempt a deadly escape.
أو القيام بمحاولة هروب مميتة.
But audiences don't come to see the magician die,
لكن الحضور لا يأتون لمشاهدة الساحر يموت،
they come to see him live.
انهم يأتون لمشاهدته يعيش.
Because the best stories
لأن القصص الأفضل
always have a happy ending.
تنتهي دوماً بنهاية سعيدة.
The tricks of magic have one special element.
الخدع السحرية لها عنصر مميز
They are stories with a twist.
انها قصص بتحريف.
Now Edward de Bono argued
و الآن يجادل ادوارد دي بونو
that our brains are pattern matching machines.
على ان أدمغتنا هي آلات لأيجاد التماثل
He said that magicians deliberately exploit
قال إن السحرة يستغلون بتعمد
the way their audiences think.
الطريقة التي يفكر بها الجمهور
Edward de Bono: Stage magic relies almost wholly
ادوارد دي بونو: يعتمد السحر المسرحي بصورة شبه كاملة
on the momentum error.
على خطأ الزخم.
The audience is led to make assumptions or elaborations
حيث يقاد الجمهور لتكوين إفتراضات أو تفسيرات
that are perfectly reasonable,
منطقية تماماً
but do not, in fact, match
لكنها في الحقيقة لا تطابق
what is being done in front of them.
ما يعرض أمامهم
MT: In that respect,
ماركو: في هذا الأتجاه
magic tricks are like jokes.
الخدع السحرية تشبه النكت
Jokes lead us down a path
النكت تسير بنا في اتجاه
to an expected destination.
ل نهاية متوقعة
But when the scenario we have imagined suddenly flips
لكن عندما ينقلب هذا السيناريو فجأة
into something entirely unexpected,
الى شيء غير متوقع بالمرة
we laugh.
نضحك.
The same thing happens
نفس الشيء يحصل
when people watch magic tricks.
عندما يشاهد الناس الخدع السحرية
The finale
الخاتمة
defies logic,
تتحدى المنطق،
gives new insight into the problem,
تعطي تبصراً جديدا للمشكلة،
and audiences express their amazement
ف يعبر الجمهور عن دهشتهم
with laughter.
بالضحك
It's fun to be fooled.
من الممتع ان تُخدَع.
One of the key qualities of all stories
أحد الصفات الرئيسية لجميع القصص
is that they're made to be shared.
هو إنها نشأت لكي يتم مشاركتها.
We feel compelled to tell them.
نشعر إننا مضطرون أن نرويها
When I do a trick at a party --
عندما أقوم بخدعة ما في حفلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that person will immediately pull their friend over
ذلك الشخص سوف يقوم فوراً بسحب صديقه
and ask me to do it again.
و يطلب مني القيام بها مرة أخرى.
They want to share the experience.
إنهم يريدون مشاركة التجربة.
That makes my job more difficult,
و هو ما يجعل عملي أكثر صعوبة
because, if I want to surprise them,
و السبب،إذا كنت اريد مفاجأتهم سوية
I need to tell a story that starts the same,
يتوجب علي ان أروي قصة تبدأ بصورة مشابهة
but ends differently --
لكنها تنتهي بصورة مختلفة
a trick with a twist
خدعة بتحريف
on a twist.
و على تحريف.
It keeps me busy.
هذا يبقيني منشغلاً
Now experts believe
الآن يؤمن الخبراء
that stories go beyond our capacity for keeping us entertained.
ان القصص تذهب وراء قدرتنا كي تبقينا مستمتعين.
We think in narrative structures.
نحن نفكر بهيكلة سردية.
We connect events and emotions
نربط الأحداث و المشاعر
and instinctively transform them
و نحولها بطريقة فطرية
into a sequence that can be easily understood.
الى تسلسل يسهل علينا فهمه
It's a uniquely human achievement.
انه إنجاز بشري بتفرد.
We all want to share our stories,
كلنا نريد أن نشارك قصصنا،
whether it is the trick we saw at the party,
سواء كانت الخدعة التي شاهدناها في الحفلة،
the bad day at the office
اليوم السيء في المكتب
or the beautiful sunset we saw on vacation.
أو مشهد الغروب الجميل الذي شاهدناه في رحلة ما
Today, thanks to technology,
اليوم -بفضل التكنولوجيا-
we can share those stories as never before,
نستطيع أن نشارك هذه القصص كما لم نفعل من قبل
by email, Facebook,
عبر البريد الألكتروني،الفيسبوك،
blogs, tweets,
المدونات الألكترونية،التغريدات،
on TED.com.
على تيد.كوم .
The tools of social networking,
أدوات التواصل الأجتماعي،
these are the digital campfires
إنها نيران المخيم الرقمية
around which the audience gathers
حيث يتجمع حولها الجمهور
to hear our story.
كي يسمع قصتنا.
We turn facts into similes and metaphors,
نحن نحول الحقائق الى تشبيهات و استعارات،
and even fantasies.
بل و حتى تخيلات.
We polish the rough edges of our lives
نصقل الزوايا الخشنة في حياتنا
so that they feel whole.
كي تبدو كاملة.
Our stories make us the people we are
قصصنا تجعلنا ما نحن عليه
and, sometimes, the people we want to be.
و -أحيانا- كما نود أن نكون عليه.
They give us our identity
إنها تمنحنا هويتنا
and a sense of community.
و شعوراً بالإنتماء الى المجتمع.
And if the story is a good one,
و اذا كانت القصة جيدة،
it might even make us smile.
من الممكن حتى ان تجعلنا نبتسم.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)